Finding Aid for Inter-Cooperative Council (Ann Arbor, Mich.) records, 1932-2012
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Inter-Cooperative Council (Ann Arbor, Mich.) records 1932-2012
Inter-Cooperative Council (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
87199; Bimu F54 2
Organization established to coordinate activities of cooperative houses founded and operated by University of Michigan students. Minutes, office files, and newsletters, also records of student cooperative, the Socialist House.
47.5 linear feet in 48 boxes
2 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This record group was the gift of the Council (donor no. 3815 ) and came to the library in several accessions beginning in 1961. Additional materials have come from the U-M Office of Student Affairs (donor no. 2948 ).
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
The Inter-Cooperative Council (hereafter ICC) was created to coordinate the activities of student-founded cooperative houses. The cooperative houses were first organized during the Depression to provide University of Michigan students with an inexpensive alternative to university operated or privately owned rental properties.
The Student Socialist Club organized the first cooperative house in 1932, named Michigan Socialist House. It was joined in 1936 by Rochdale House, a cooperative organized with the active assistance of Rev. H. L. Pickerill, student pastor of the Ann Arbor Disciples Church. In 1937 a third house, Alice Freeman Palmer House, organized itself. Both Rochdale and Palmer houses were organized along Rochdale principles, which included democratic operation, opposition to discrimination on the basis of race or religion and a neutral political position.
In 1937 the three independent houses decided to form a joint body to enable them to purchase items in quantity. The organization formed was the Inter-Cooperative Council. Increasingly the ICC took on additional tasks. By 1941 the organization was responsible for all the houses' financing and the assignment of personnel to the various houses.
In 1941 the ICC reached a pre-World War II peak of 12 houses. The war witnessed a decline in the number of affiliated houses, reflecting the overall decline in the student population. By war's end only 5 houses were still functioning.
During World War II the ICC made a major policy change regarding the ownership of its constituent houses. Originally the structures occupied by ICC houses were rented. Difficulties regarding leases led the ICC to adopt, in 1944, a policy that the organization obtain legal title to all of the properties which constituent houses occupied. The decision to buy rather than rent property was quickly and successfully implemented. In 1950 of the six houses affiliated with the ICC, the organization held title to five of them and plans were well underway to purchase the sixth.
Throughout the postwar period and continuing into the 1950s the ICC was plagued by slow growth and internal disputes. The most pressing internal difficulty involved a proposal to hire a full-time executive secretary to work for the ICC. Proponents saw the plan as a simple necessity in light of the ICC's acquisition of much property. Opponents argued that a full time, non-student employee would fatally compromise the Rochdale principle of democratic decision making. In 1951 the organization conducted a referendum in which the proposal to hire a full-time executive secretary narrowly passed. Opposition to the idea, however, continued throughout the 1950s. Luther Buchele was selected as first executive secretary of the ICC. He would serve in this capacity until 1985.
In the early 1950s the ICC expressed an interest in obtaining property on the University of Michigan's North Campus for eventual expansion. Long and troubled negotiations with the University ensued, with many ICC members coming to believe that the University was purposely delaying the project. Specifically they felt the University Housing authorities and those responsible for student regulations saw the ICC as a competitor in the housing market and as an often effective source of opposition to student regulations. In any event, the long negotiations between university officials and the ICC culminated eventually in the construction of a large cooperative housing complex on North Campus, ground being broken for the project in 1969. In addition to the North Campus project, the ICC purchased several new properties in the central campus area during the 1960s and early 1970s. In 1979 the ICC owned 13 properties in the central campus area, as well as the North Campus complex. The next three decades would see further expansion and house reorganization.
Further information about the organization's history will be found in the volume In our own hands; a history of student housing cooperatives at the University of Michigan (1994). This volume is located in the collection.
The records of the ICC cover the years 1932 to 2012 and are divided into ten series: Minutes, Office Files, Printed Materials, Events and Programs, Organizational Topical Files, Correspondence Files, Collected Research Materials, House Records, External Organizations, and Audio-Visual Materials.
Subjects:
University of Michigan--Student housing.; Socialist House (University of Michigan); University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1931-1940.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1941-1950.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1951-1960.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1961-1970.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1971-1980.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1981-1990.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1991-2000.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--2001-2010.; Inter-Cooperative Council (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Cooperative societies--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Cooperatives--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Dwellings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Inter-Cooperative Council (Ann Arbor, Mich.); University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1971-1980.; University of Michigan--Student housing--1971-1980.; University of Michigan--Student housing--1981-1990.; University of Michigan--Student housing--1991-2000.; University of Michigan--Student housing--2001-2010.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs.; University of Michigan--Student housing--1971-1980.; University of Michigan--Student housing--1981-1990.
Genre Terms:
Albums.; Audiocassettes.; CD-ROMs.; Manuals.; Newsletters.; Oral histories.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Student publications.; Tape reels.; Videotapes.
- Minutes
  The first series, the minutes file (1937-2005), originally consisted exclusively of minutes of meetings of the Board of Directors. In the 1960s, these files began including (in addition) minutes of various committees created by the board (e.g. Development Committee) and of meetings of the various houses. The series also contains bound volumes of minutes from the Board of Directors and the Education Committee. These may duplicate material found in the first part of this series.
  - Index to Minutes (Box 1)
  - 1937-1967, 31 folders (Box 1)
  - 1968-1976, 22 folders (Box 2)
  - 1977-1986, 5 folders (Box 3)
- Office files
  The office files (1932-1990) originally contained all documents other than the minutes, including all committee and officer reports, and all miscellaneous documents. The distinction between the two files, however, slowly began to break down. Increasingly documents related to the minutes, such as reports and documents related to items on the agenda, were filed with the minutes, while copies of the minutes found their way into the office files. By the 1970s the distinction between the two files had become largely artificial. After 1980, documentation in the office files is scattered.
  - Index to Minutes (Box 1)
  - 1937-1967, 31 folders (Box 1)
  - 1968-1976, 22 folders (Box 2)
  - 1977-1986, 5 folders (Box 3)
  - 1994-2001, 22 folders (Box 22)
  - 2004-2005, 4 folders (Box 22)
  - Bound volumes of minutes 1940-1998
    - 1940-1949 (Box 23)
    - 1943-1944 1946-1948 (Box 23)
    - 1950-1953 (Box 23)
    - 1963-1969 (Box 23)
    - 1970-1980, 5 volumes (Box 23)
    - 1981-April 1987, 8 volumes (Box 24)
    - May 1987-April 1994, 7 volumes (Box 25)
    - Education committee 1975-1998, 4 volumes (Box 26)
- Office Files
  The Office Files (1932-1990) originally contained all documents other than the minutes, including all committee and officer reports, and all miscellaneous documents. The distinction between the two files, however, slowly began to break down. Increasingly documents related to the minutes, such as reports and documents related to items on the agenda, were filed with the minutes, while copies of the minutes found their way into the office files. By the 1970s the distinction between the two files had become largely artificial. After 1980, documentation in the Office Files is scattered.
  - 1932- circa 1947 (Michigan Socialist House Scrapbook) (Box 3)
  - Ca. 1932 (Michigan Socialist House) (Box 3)
  - 1936 (Michigan Socialist House Applications) (Box 3)
  - 1939 (Michigan Socialist House Applications) (Box 3)
  - 1937-1939 (Including Owen House Book, 1938-1953) (Box 3)
  - 1940-1950, 13 folders (Box 3)
  - 1950-1958 (Full Time Secretary) (Box 3)
  - 1951 (Survey) (Box 3)
  - 1951-1953, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - 1954-1963, 22 folders (Box 4)
  - 1964-1974, 26 folders (Box 5)
  - 1975-1990, 14 folders (Box 6)
  - 1940s-1960s (Box 6)
  - 1943-1954 (Box 6)
    (formerly in binder)
  - 1954-1962 (Box 6)
  - 1963-1964 (Box 6)
- Printed materials
  Printed Materials (1939-2011) are divided into two subseries: Manuals and Newsletters. The manuals provide how-to instruction in such diverse topics as food preparation, house maintenance, financial and accounts management, and the duties and responsibilities of co-op members. The newsletters include nearly complete runs of the Cooperator, Alumni Cooperator, and the Weekly Cooperator. The members of the Inter-Cooperative Council also produced other newsletters such as The Bridge, The Co-op Eccentric, and the ICC's Bi-Weekly.
  - Manuals
    - Accounting for the Simpleton 1955-1971 (Box 6)
    - The Accountant's Manifesto: For the Use of Accountants of Cooperative Houses at the University of Michigan 1956-1983 (Box 6)
    - Accounting Made Simple undated (Box 6)
    - Board Manual 1988-1996 (Box 6)
    - The Compleat Work Manager 1990 (Box 6)
    - Confidential Guide to Co-op Management: A Manual for Co-op House Managers 1966, 1974, 1977 (Box 6)
    - Confidential Guide to House Management 1974, 1988 (Box 6)
    - Confidential Guide to CO-OP House Management and House Maintenance Book 1977 (Box 6)
    - Co-op Maintenance Book 1974 (Box 6)
    - The Co-op President's Savoir-Faire 1982 (Box 6)
    - The Co-op President's Vade Mecum or How to Live With the Personnel Committee Bureaucracy 1966, 1969 (Box 6)
    - Cooperative Marketing Handbook circa 1939 (Box 6)
    - Co-ops at the University of Michigan circa 1950 (Box 6)
    - Coordinating Committee Manual 2005-2006 (Box 6)
    - Development Committee Working Manual 1994-1995 (Box 6)
    - ERC Manual 1982 (Box 6)
    - Food and Kitchen Management Training Manual (Box 6)
    - House Directors' Manual 1966 (Box 6)
    - House Maintenance & Management 1974 (Box 6)
    - House Manager/Work Manager Manual 1986-1987 (Box 6)
    - ICC Board Manual 1981-1982, 1987 (Box 7)
    - ICC Operating Procedures of the Membership Committee 1982 (Box 7)
    - Keeping within the food budget 1980, 1983 (Box 7)
    - Maintenance Manual 1989-1993 (Box 7)
    - Meals for the Masses: A Cookbook for the ICC 1979 (Box 7)
    - Member Handbook 1976 (Box 7)
    - Owner's Manual for the Inter-Cooperative Council at the University of Michigan 1992 (Box 7)
    - Owner's Manual ... 2000 (Box 7)
    - The Personnel chairman's Vade Mecum or How to Live with Bureaucracy 1956 (Box 7)
    - Revised President's Manual (Box 7)
    - Stewards' Baedeker: A Manual for Co-op Stewards 1966-1988 (Box 7)
    - Steward's Manual 1962, 1982 (Box 7)
    - Treasurer's Manual 1989-1990 (Box 7)
  - Newsletters
    - A Word About Student Co-ops: For Residence Advisors and House Mothers Undated (Box 7)
    - Work Manager's Intercooperative Manual 1993 (Box 7)
    - Cooperator and Alumni Cooperator, 1939-1968, 27 folders (Box 7)
    - Cooperator and Alumni Cooperator, 1969-2012, 25 folders (Box 8)
    - Weekly Cooperator / Co-op Reporter, undated, 1974, 1983-1984, 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Weekly Cooperator / Co-op Reporter, 1985-2012, 21 folders (Box 9)
    - Various
      - Antwerp, 1975 (Box 9)
      - The Bridge, 1957 (Box 9)
      - Co-op Departer, 1983 (Box 9)
      - The Co-op Eccentric, 1982-1985, 3 folders (Box 9)
      - The House Organ, 1972-1975, 4 folders (Box 9)
      - The ICC Cooperator, 1978 (Box 9)
      - The ICC Newsletter, 1970 (Box 9)
      - ICC Nooz and Comment, 1971 (Box 9)
      - ICC Summer News, 1973 (Box 9)
      - ICC Summer Review, 1972 (Box 9)
      - ICC's Bi Weekly, 1970-1971, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Maintenance Standard, 1991 (Box 9)
      - Mother Co-op News, 1974 (Box 9)
      - News Notes, 1975 (Box 9)
      - Pot, 1966 (Box 9)
      - The Summer Cooperator, 1974-2004, 1 volumes; 2 folders (Box 9)
- Events and Programs
  The Events and Programs series (1944-2009) consists of materials created in the planning and execution of various events and programs for the ICC. The materials are arranged in eight subseries by event. Annual events or programs appear first, arranged alphabetically: Annual meetings, Cooperator-in-residence program, Summer Education program, and Training, orientation sessions, and retreats. These are followed by periodic events: ICC-wide anniversary celebrations, House reunions, Regional reunions and then Miscellaneous. Within each subseries (with the exception of the Miscellaneous subseries), materials are arranged chronologically.
  - Annual meetings
    - 1944-2009, 7 folders (Box 39)
  - Cooperator-in-residence program
    - Background/history (Box 39)
    - OSCA Residency program (Box 39)
    - Cooperator-in-residence files 1987-2000, 7 folders (Box 39)
  - Summer Education Program
    - Background/history (Box 39)
    - Schedules, advertising, and photographs
      - 1987-1997, 3 folders (Box 39)
        (formerly in a binder)
      - 1998-2008, 2 folders (Box 39)
    - Program planning and evaluation materials 1987-2002, 16 folders (Box 40)
  - Training, orientation sessions, and retreats
    - Board of Directors 1978, 1983-2009, 27 folders (Box 41)
    - Coordinating Committee 1993-2008, 4 folders (Box 42)
    - House Officers 1977-2008, 23 folders (Box 42)
    - North Campus Officers 1980s, 1990s (Box 42)
    - New Members 1989-2007, 14 folders (Box 42)
  - ICC-wide anniversary celebrations
    - 25th anniversary of Luther Buchele's employment ("Luther Day")
      - Articles, correspondence, reflection essay 1976 (Box 43)
      - Letter of congratulations from R. W. Fleming 1976 (Box 43)
        (originally in frame)
      - Proposal for "Luther Day 2," 1998 (Box 43)
    - 50th anniversary of the founding of the first Ann Arbor co-op
      - Schedule 1983 (Box 43)
    - 50th anniversary of the founding of the ICC
      - Mixed materials 1987, 4 folders (Box 43)
      - Planning and other materials 1987 (Box 43)
    - 50th anniversary of the incorporation of the ICC
      - Mixed materials 1986-1994 (Box 43)
      - Mixed materials 1994, 7 folders (Box 43)
      - News media 1993-1994 (Box 43)
      - Presidents' Breakfast and Co-op Histories transcriptions 1994 (Box 43)
    - 60th anniversary of incorporation and home ownership
      - Homecoming program booklet 2004 (Box 43)
  - House Reunions (including anniversary celebrations)
    - Proposal for annual "homecoming," November 1986 (Box 43)
    - Lester 1990 (Box 43)
    - Brandeis 1991 (Box 43)
    - Congress 1992 (Box 43)
    - Stevens 1994 (Box 43)
    - North Campus 1995 (Box 43)
  - Regional reunions
    - Berkley June 1997 (Box 43)
    - DC April 1998 (Box 43)
    - Boston July 1998 (Box 43)
    - New York City May 1999 (Box 43)
  - Miscellaneous
    - ACE Institute 2002 (Box 43)
    - AIDS Awareness Symposium 1992 (Box 43)
    - BASH 1990-2006, 2 folders (Box 43)
    - Cooperative Communicators Association Annual Institute 1994 (Box 43)
    - NASCO Institute 1989-2005, 3 folders (Box 43)
    - New directions symposium 1984 (Box 43)
    - Wind Through the Pines symposium 1977 (Box 43)
    - Winds of Change retreat 1992 (Box 43)
- Organizational Topical files
  The Organizational Topical Files (1932-2012) series includes annual reports, directories, and financial reports, as well as prospectuses which describe plans for a North Campus cooperative. This series also contains histories of the Inter-Cooperative Council such as In Our Own Hands: A History of Student Housing Cooperatives at the University of Michigan (1994). This volume has a detailed account of the development of the Inter-Cooperative Council at the University of Michigan with a list of the ICC presidents, a time-line which includes the purchase date and address of the various houses, and excellent photographs of the houses, residents, and house activities. Other materials in this series include those related to this "history book project," the Alumni association, committees (such as the Education Committee or the Diversity Committee), and Ann Arbor community relations.
  - Advocacy Project 1990-1992 (Box 10)
  - Alumni Association (ICC)
    - Annual meeting materials 1996 (Box 10)
    - Constitution 1994-1996 (Box 10)
    - Membership renewal solicitations 1998 (Box 10)
    - Memo from Jim Jones to Louise Hartung 1996 (Box 10)
    - Mixed materials 1993-1997 (Box 10)
    - Program surveys 1995 (Box 10)
    - Proposal 1993-1994 (Box 10)
    - Steering committee 1993-1995 (Box 10)
    - Video planning and budgets 1993-1994 (Box 10)
  - Alumni Council (ICC)
    - Budget and meeting agenda 1998 (Box 10)
    - Election ballots 1998 (Box 10)
    - Handbook 1998 (Box 10)
    - Meeting materials
      - 1995 (Box 10)
      - 1996-1997 (Box 10)
    - Mixed materials 1995-1999 (Box 10)
  - Alumni list
    - 1932-1955 (Box 10)
    - Congress 1940-1943 alumni as of March 1989 (Box 10)
  - Alumni relations
    - 2-year budget proposals 1988 (Box 10)
    - Bequests information 1992-1993 (Box 10)
    - Correspondence and board meeting minutes 1976 (Box 10)
    - Fundraising/membership drive 1992-1995 (Box 10)
    - ICC solicitation/donation letters (Box 10)
    - Letters to alumni 1976 (Box 10)
    - Program materials 1970s, 1980s (Box 10)
    - Publications information and finances 1997 (Box 10)
    - Reunions and visits correspondence and announcements 1991 (Box 10)
    - Scholarship bequest: Miriam Olshansky Zahler Fund 1996 (Box 10)
    - Travel/tour planning (Box 10)
  - Alumni reminiscences
    - Jean and John King, Harold L. Ehlers, and others (Box 10)
    - Two Dollar House 1942, photocopy of typed version (Box 10)
  - Ann Arbor community relations
    - Ann Arbor Non-Profit Housing Development Corporation 1988 (Box 10)
    - City of Ann Arbor 1986-1987 (Box 10)
    - Community Development Corporation 1987 (Box 10)
    - Community Housing Coalition circa 1985 (Box 10)
    - Correspondence 1987 (Box 10)
    - Old Fourth Ward Association 1985-1989 (Box 10)
    - Outreach circa 1985 (Box 10)
    - Oxbridge Neighborhood Association, Information on 1617 Washtenaw and the ICC, circa 1995 (Box 10)
    - Oxbridge Neighborhood Association 1997-1999 (Box 10)
  - Ann Arbor Historic District Commission, 23rd Annual Ann Arbor Preservation Awards 2011 (Box 10)
  - Ann Arbor housing code issues 1963, 1976 (Box 10)
  - Ann Arbor zoning issues
    - A-1 zone proposal materials 1951 (Box 10)
    - R2B / R4A classification challenge 1963-1964 (Box 10)
    - R2B zone correspondence and other materials 1973-1974, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Housing code revisions 1976 (Box 10)
  - Annual Reports
    - 1944-1998, 1 volumes (Box 10)
      (some issues missing)
    - 1998-2007 (Box 11)
    - 2009-2012 (Box 11)
  - Annual reviews 1990s (Box 11)
  - Anthologies: Collected Writings from Ancient Days in Co-ops, 1948-1960 (Box 11)
  - Bentley Historical Library
    - Correspondence and finding aids 1980-2010 (Box 11)
    - Detailed notes on contents of ICC records at BHL 1991-1992 (Box 11)
  - Board of Directors
    - Manual 1985 (Box 11)
    - Manual 1990s (Box 11)
    - Member lists (Box 11)
    - Miscellaneous materials (Box 11)
    - Notebook 1980s (Box 11)
    - Operating procedures 1969 (Box 11)
  - Brandeis House, reports to the Board of Directors 1970s-1980s (Box 11)
  - Brochures undated, 1951-1983 (Box 11)
  - Buchele, Luther
    - Artwork by Luther and Wesley (Box 11)
    - Correspondence with Joel Welty 1957-1959 (Box 11)
    - Induction into the Cooperative Hall of Fame 1987 (Box 11)
    - Mixed material (speeches, reports, etc.), 4 folders (Box 11)
    - Personal/family correspondence 1951-1963 (Box 11)
    - Testimony before Michigan State Senate 1969 (Box 11)
  - By-Laws / Rules of the Organization, 3 folders (Box 11)
  - By-Laws / Rules of the Organization, 1 folders (Box 12)
  - By-laws, constitution, standings rules, etc. 1940s, 1950s (Box 12)
  - Clippings, 10 folders (Box 12)
  - Clippings with articles about ICC, pre-1950s-1960s, 3 folders (Box 12)
  - Coeducational Housing Study Committee 1970 (Box 12)
  - Committee reports and recommendations circa 1990 (Box 12)
  - Committees, mixed 1980s (Box 12)
  - Cooperative buying 1941-1962 (Box 12)
  - "Criticism of beards spurs..." 1967 (Box 12)
  - Development Committee materials 1960s-1980s (Box 12)
  - Directories of officers and members, various dates 1957-1980 (Box 12)
  - Diversity committee (Box 13)
    - Handbook 2003 (Box 13)
    - Minutes, correspondence, and other materials 2007-2011, 4 folders (Box 13)
  - Education center
    - ICC Philosophy, goals (Box 13)
    - Programs/projects (Box 13)
    - Purpose/policy (Box 13)
    - Study Hall monitors (Box 13)
    - Origins/History (Box 13)
  - Education Committee
    - Recruiting people/ideas (Box 13)
    - Self-sponsored events/activities (Box 13)
  - Executive secretary's reports 1950s-1960s (Box 13)
  - Expansion fund materials 1969-1996 (Box 13)
  - Federal Aid to Education bill, correspondence and legislation 1949 (Box 13)
  - Finance Committee instructions 1940s (Box 13)
  - Financial Reports: Audit Reports and budgets 1955-1990, 4 folders (Box 13)
  - Fraternity -- Sorority -- Cooperative housing code study group 1977 (Box 13)
  - Fund raising drives (Box 13)
  - General information about student cooperatives, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Histories
    - The History of the Cooperative Movement at the University of Michigan, 1979 (Box 13)
    - In Our Own Hands: A History of Student Housing Cooperatives at the University of Michigan, 1994 (Box 13)
  - Historical information
    - General early history 1930s-1940s (Box 13)
    - Mixed 1938-2004 (Box 13)
  - History of the ICC, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - History book project (Box 45)
    - Corrections/correspondence 1993, 1997 (Box 45)
    - Fan mail 1994-1995 (Box 45)
    - Planning materials 1993-1994 (Box 45)
    - Printing estimates 1994 (Box 45)
    - Records of complimentary copies distributed 1994 (Box 45)
    - "Stories for the book of apocrypha" (original folder label) 1983-1998 (Box 45)
  - History display
    - General outline/plans 1994 (Box 45)
    - List of ideas, report, and research materials (Box 45)
    - Possible [items] for wall display (Box 45)
    - Wall display materials (including various ICC quotes) (Box 45)